Register of the Pathfinder Press Publications, 1922-2014
Hoover Institution Archives
- RELATED FOREIGN IMPRINTS, 1937-1993 (Box 32-39)
  - Argentina (Box 32)
    - Reed, Evelyn. Problemas de la liberacion de la mujer [Problems of Women's Liberation. Spanish translation] Buenos Aires: Ediciones Pluma, 67 p. Cf. Merit (1969) and Pathfinder (1970) imprints, 1974.
    - Mandela, Nelson. Intensifiquemos la lucha [Intensify the Struggle to Abolish Apartheid. Spanish translation] Buenos Aires: Ediciones Letra Buena, 110 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1990) imprint, 1991.
  - Belgium. Castro, Fidel. Cuba en de strijd voor het socialisme in de jaren '90. By Fidel Castro and Ernesto Che Guevara. Eric Wils, 34 p., ca. 1990.
  - Brazil. Reed, Evelyn. Sexo contra sexo ou classe contra classe [Problems of Women's Liberation. Portuguese translation] Sao Paulo: Proposta Editorial/Versus, 113 p. Cf. Merit (1969) and Pathfinder (1970) imprints, 1980.
  - Canada
    - Fourth International. Against Wall Street and the Kremlin: Manifesto of the Second World Congress of the Fourth International to the Exploited Masses of the World. Toronto: Workers Press, 48 p. Cf. France imprint, 1948.
    - Novack, George. Who Will Change the World? The New Left and the Views of C. Wright Mills. Toronto: Young Socialist Forum, 36 p., 1966.
    - Cannon, James P. Le parti revolutionnaire [The Revolutionary Party. French translation] Montreal: Editions d'Avant-Garde, 34 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1975) imprint, ca. 1970s.
    - League for Socialist Action/Ligue Socialiste Ouvriere. For an Independent and Socialist Quebec. Toronto: Vanguard Publications, 33 p., 1971.
    - Cannon, James P. La lutte pour un parti proletarien. Montreal: Editions d'Avant-Garde, 40 p., 1975.
    - Poulin, Richard. Le maoisme: Mythe et realite. By Richard Poulin, Katie Curtin and David Frankel. Montreal: Editions d'Avant-Garde, 48 p., 1976.
    - Fidler, Richard. Canada: Accomplice in Apartheid. Vanguard Publications, 23 p., 1977.
  - Colombia
    - Trotsky, Leon. La segunda revolucion China: Notas y escritos de 1919 a 1938. Bogota: Editorial Pluma, 219 p., 1976.
    - Novack, George. La ley del desarrollo desigual y combinado. By George Novack, Leon Trotsky and Nahuel Moreno. Bogota: Editorial Pluma, 122 p. Cf. Pioneer (1965) and Merit (1966) imprints, 1977.
    - Novack, George. Para comprender la historia [Understanding History. Spanish translation] 2nd edition. Bogota: Editorial Pluma, 175 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1980) imprint, 1977.
    - Novack, George. Las tres primeras internacionales: Su historia y sus lecciones [The First Three Internationals. Spanish translation] By George Novack, Dave Frankel and Fred Feldman. Bogota: Editorial Pluma, 277 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1974) imprint, 1977.
  - Cuba. Mandela, Nelson. Habla Nelson Mandela [Nelson Mandela Speaks. Spanish translation] Havana: Editora Politica, 84 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1986) imprint, 1987.
  - France
    - Fourth International. Contre Wall Street et le Kremlin: Manifeste du deuxieme congres de la Quatrieme Internationale aux exploites du monde entier [Against Wall Street and the Kremlin. French translation] Toulouse, 39 p. Cf. Canada imprint, 1948.
    - X, Malcolm. Le pouvoir noir [Malcolm X Speaks. French translation] Edited by George Breitman. Paris: Francois Maspero, 264 p. Cf. Merit (1965) and Pathfinder (1989) imprints, 1966.
    - Mandel, Ernest. Marxism vs. Ultraleftism: Key Issues in Healy's Challenge to the Fourth International. By Ernest Germain [pseudonym] Paris: Fourth International, 97 p., 1967.
    - Trotsky, Leon. Escritos sobre Espana. Paris: Ruedo Iberico, 301 p., 1971.
    - Dobbs, Farrell. La revolte des camionneurs [Teamster Rebellion. French translation] Paris: Centre d'Etudes et de Recherches sur les Mouvements Trotskyste et Revolutionnaires Internationaux, 1988. [Its Cahiers, No. 5 p. Cf. Monad (1972) imprint, 51] 13
    - X, Malcolm. Derniers discours [Last Speeches. French translation] Paris: Editions Dagorno, 188 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1989) imprint
    - Cannon, James P. La lutte pour un parti proletarien [The Struggle for a Proletarian Party. Abridged French translation] Paris: Centre d'Etudes et de Recherches sur les Mouvements Trotskyste et Revolutionnaires Internationaux, 1990. [Its Cahiers, No. p. Cf. Pathfinder (1972) imprint, 56] 64
  - Germany. Cannon, James P. Der Kampf fur eine proletarische Partei [The Struggle for a Proletarian Party. German translation] Frankfurt: Internationale Sozialistische Publikationen, 112 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1972) imprint, 1982. (Box 33)
  - Great Britain
    - Kutcher, James. The Case of the Legless Veteran. London: New Park Publications, 178 p. Subsequent edition published by Monad Press (1973, q.v.), 1953.
    - Trotsky, Leon. The New Course. London: New Park Publications, 111 p., 1956.
    - The Twentieth Congress (C.P.S.U.) and World Trotskyism: A Documented Analysis. London: New Park Publications, 124 p., 1957.
    - Trotsky, Leon. My Life: An Attempt at an Autobiography. Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 628 p. Reprint of Pathfinder Press edition (1970, q.v.), 1975.
    - Trotsky, Leon. The Struggle against Fascism in Germany. Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 506 p. Reprint of Pathfinder Press edition (1971, q.v.), 1975.
  - Greece
    - Jenness, Doug. Polemos kai epanastase sto Bietnam [War and Revolution in Vietnam. Greek translation] Athens: Neon Bibliopoleion, 32 p. Cf. Related U.S. (1965) imprint, 1966.
    - Morrow, Felix. Epanastase kai antepanastase stin Ispania [Revolution and Counter-revolution in Spain. Greek translation] Athens: Ekdoseis "Atrapos", 286 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1974) imprint, 1977.
    - Novack, George. Anthropismos kai sosialismos [Humanism and Socialism. Greek translation] Athens: Ekdoseiz A. Libanis "Nea Sinora", 178 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1973) imprint, 1978.
    - Reed, Evelyn. Sexismos kai episteme [Sexism and Science. Greek translation] Athens: Theoria, 237 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1978) imprint, 1981.
    - Novack, George. Eisagoge ste logike tou marxismou [An Introduction to the Logic of Marxism. Greek translation] Athens: Protoporiake Bibliotheke, 147 p. Cf. Related U.S. (1942), Pioneer (1963), Merit (1966) and Pathfinder (1971) imprints, 1982.
  - Hong Kong. Evans, Les. Mao Tse-tung i hon te Chung-kuo [China after Mao. Chinese translation] Hong Kong: Shih Yueh chu pan she, 189 p. Cf. Monad (1978) imprint, 1981.
  - Iceland. Byltingin i Nicaragua: Raedur og rit sandinista. Reykjavik: Sigurlaug S. Gunnlaugsdottir, 132 p., 1989.
  - India
    - Hansen, Joseph. [Is Marxism Obsolete? Gujarati translation] Baroda, 52 p., 1975.
    - Novack, George. [Democracy and Revolution. Gujarati translation] Ahmedabad, 386 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1971) imprint, 1975.
    - Reed, Evelyn. [Problems of Women's Liberation. Gujarati translation] 176 p. Cf. Merit (1969) and Pathfinder (1970) imprints, 1978.
  - Iran
    - Cannon, James P. Muhakamah-'i susyalism [Socialism on Trial. Persian translation] Tehran: Shirkat-i Nashr-i Fanus, 184 p. Cf. Pioneer (1942), Merit (1969) and Pathfinder (1973) imprints, 1980.
    - Reed, Evelyn. Insan dar 'asr-i tavahhush [Woman's Evolution. Persian translation] Tehran: Intisharat-i Hashimi, 2 volumes. Cf. Pathfinder (1974) imprint, 1984/1985. (Box 34)
  - Italy
    - Breitman, George. Malcolm X: L'uomo, le idee i miti [Malcolm X: The Man and His Ideas. Italian translation] Rome: Samona e Savelli, 109 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1979) imprint, 1968.
    - Leon, Abram. Il marxismo e la questione ebraica [The Jewish Question. Italian translation] Rome: Samona e Savelli, 237 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1970) imprint, 1968.
    - Vernon, Robert. Il ghetto negro [The Black Ghetto. Italian translation] Rome: Samona e Savelli, 51 p. Cf. Merit (1969) imprint, 1968.
    - X, Malcolm. Ultimi discorsi [Malcolm X Speaks. Italian translation] Edited by George Breitman. Turin: Giulio Einaudi, 371 p. Cf. Merit (1965) and Pathfinder (1989) imprints, 1968.
    - Waters, Mary-Alice. Maoismo e potere negro [Maoism in the U.S. Italian translation] Rome: Samona e Savelli, 96 p. Cf. Related U.S. (1969) imprint, 1970.
    - Reed, Evelyn. Sesso contro sesso o classe contro classe? Il mito dell'inferiorita della donna [Problems of Women's Liberation. Italian translation] Rome: Edizione Savelli, 189 p. Cf. Merit (1969) and Pathfinder (1970) imprints, 1973.
    - X, Malcolm. Con ogni mezzo: Discorsi e interviste [By Any Means Necessary. Italian translation] Edited by George Breitman. Turin: Giulio Einaudi, 188 p., 1973.
    - ----------. Con ogni mezzo necessario: Discorsi e interviste. Milan: Shake Edizioni Underground, 183 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1970) imprint, 1993.
    - Cannon, James P. I primi dieci anni del Partito comunista americano [The First Ten Years of American Communism. Italian translation] Milan: Jaca, 377 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1973) imprint, 1977.
  - Japan
    - X, Malcolm. Kokujin wa teiko-suru. Tokyo: Kokujin Shiso Kenkyuukai, 86 p., 1965.
    - Guevara, Ernesto. Kakumei Guevara wa kataru [Che Guevara Speaks. Japanese translation] Edited by George Lavan [pseudonym of George Weissman] Tokyo: Godo, 242 p., 1968.
    - ----------. Revised edition. Tokyo: Toshio Miyahara and Godo Shuppan-sha, 217 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1987) imprint, 1968.
    - X, Malcolm. Kokujin wa buso suru [Malcolm X Speaks. Japanese translation] Edited by George Breitman. Tokyo: San'ichi, 264 p. Cf. Merit (1965) and Pathfinder (1989) imprints, 1968.
    - Trotsky, Leon. Katoteki koryo [The Transitional Program. Japanese translation] Tokyo: Shin Jidaisha, 51 p. Cf. Pioneer (1946) and Pathfinder (1970) imprints, 1972. (Box 35)
    - Dobbs, Farrell. Timusataa no hanran [Teamster Rebellion. Japanese translation] Tokyo: Tsuge Shobo, 266 p. Cf. Monad (1972) imprint, 1973.
    - Leon, Abram. Yudayajin mondai no shi-teki tenkai [The Jewish Question. Japanese translation] Tokyo: Tsuge Shobo, 278 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1970) imprint, 1973.
    - Blanco, Hugo. Tochi ka shi ka [Land or Death. Japanese translation] Tokyo: Tsuge Shobo, 284 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1972) imprint, 1974.
    - Chiri no Higeki [Disaster in Chile. Japanese translation] Edited by Les Evans. Tokyo: Tsuge Shobo, 238 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1974) imprint
    - Reed, Evelyn. Sei no shinwa [Problems of Women's Liberation. Japanese translation] Tokyo: Tsuge Shobo, 257 p. Cf. Merit (1969) and Pathfinder (1970) imprints, 1974.
    - Chika Roshiya no koe [Samizdat. Japanese translation] Edited by George Saunders [pseudonym of George Shriver] Tokyo: Tsuge Shobo, 374 p. Cf. Monad (1974) imprint
  - Mexico
    - Trotsky, Leon. Yo acuso [I Stake My Life! Spanish translation] Mexico City: Ediciones "Nueva Era", 53 p. Cf. Pioneer (1937) imprint
    - Goldman, Albert. Quien esta detras del asesino de Leon Trotsky: Los hechos y los argumentos que prueban la culpabilidad de Stalin [The Assassination of Leon Trotsky. Spanish translation] Mexico City: Editorial Clave, p. Cf. Pioneer (1940) imprint, 1940? 90
    - King, Martin Luther. La protesta negra. By Martin Luther King, James Baldwin and Malcolm X. Mexico City: Ediciones Era, 138 p., 1965.
    - Jenness, Doug. Lenin como organizador de campanas electorales [Lenin as Election Campaign Manager. Spanish translation] Folletos Bandera Socialista, 22 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1971) imprint, ca. 1970s.
    - Trotsky, Leon. Discusiones con Trotsky sobre el programa de transicion. Folletos Bandera Socialista, 123 p., ca. 1970s.
    - Waters, Mary-Alice. Rosa Luxemburgo: Una apreciacion marxista. Folletos Bandera Socialista, 41 p., ca. 1970s.
    - Trotsky, Leon. La revolucion China. Mexico City: Editorial Grijalbo, 158 p., 1970.
    - Novack, George. Introduccion a la logica del marxismo [An Introduction to the Logic of Marxism. Spanish translation] Juventud Marxista Revolucionaria, 83 p. Cf. Related U.S. (1942), Pioneer (1963), Merit (1966) and Pathfinder (1971) imprints, 1972.
    - Trotsky, Leon. Obras de Leon Trotsky. Mexico City: Juan Pablos Editor, Volumes 1-5, 9-12, 14-16, 19-22. Includes two variant printings of Volume 4, 1972-1975. (Box 35-37)
    - Trotsky, Leon. Como hicimos la revolucion de octubre. Mexico City: Editorial Grijalbo, 156 p., 1975. (Box 37)
    - Feldman, Fred. Los avances anticapitalistas en Vietnam. Ediciones Antid Oto, p. Country of publication uncertain, 1976? 65
    - Trotsky, Leon. Imagenes de Lenin. 2nd edition. Mexico City: Ediciones Era, 148 p., 1976.
    - Yanez, Anibal. Guatemala: La lucha por la libertad [The Struggle for Freedom in Guatemala. Spanish version] Folletos Bandera Socialista, 29 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1981) imprint, 1983.
    - Reed, Evelyn. Sexo contra sexo o clase contra clase [Problems of Women's Liberation. Spanish translation] Mexico City: Fontamara, 162 p., 1984.
    - ----------. 2nd edition. Mexico City: Fontamara, 162 p. Cf. Merit (1969) and Pathfinder (1970) imprints, 1987.
    - Novack, George. Para comprender la historia [Understanding History. Spanish translation] 2nd edition. Mexico City: Fontamara, 213 p., 1986.
    - ----------. 3rd edition. Mexico City: Fontamara, 213 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1980) imprint, 1989.
    - Reed, Evelyn. La evolucion de la mujer: Del clan matriarcal a la familia patriarcal [Woman's Evolution. Spanish translation] Mexico City: Fontamara, 350 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1974) imprint, 1987.
  - Nepal. Reed, Evelyn. [Is Biology Woman's Destiny? Nepali translation] Kathmandu: Parizat, 28 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1972) imprint, 1984.
  - Netherlands
    - Reed, Evelyn. Welke emancipatie? Beshouwingen over de bevrijding van de vrouw [Problems of Women's Liberation. Dutch translation] The Hague: Stichting Uitgeverij, 55 p. Cf. Merit (1969) and Pathfinder (1970) imprints
    - X, Malcolm. Malcolm X spreekt: Over de Afro-Amerikaanse geschiedenis [Malcolm X on Afro-American History. Dutch translation] EPO Uitgeverij, 99 p. Cf. Merit (1967) and Pathfinder (1970) imprints, 1993.
  - Portugal. Novack, George. O marxismo e o desenvolvimento na natureza e na sociedade: Lei do desenvolvimento desigual e combinado [Uneven and Combined Development in History. Portuguese translation] Porto: Ediciones Pluma, 38 p. Cf. Pioneer (1965) and Merit (1966) imprints, 1974.
  - Spain
    - Trotsky, Leon. Manual del soldado rojo. Barcelona: Editorial Marxista, 20 p., 1937.
    - Jenness, Linda. Feminismo y socialismo. 16 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1972) imprint, ca. 1970s.
    - La Oposicion de izquierda en la U.R.S.S. By Leon Trotsky et al. Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 201 p., 1977.
    - Reed, Evelyn. Sexo contra sexo o clase contra clase [Problems of Women's Liberation. Spanish translation] Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 162 p. Cf. Merit (1969) and Pathfinder (1970) imprints, 1977.
    - Trotsky, Leon. En defensa del marxismo [In Defense of Marxism. Spanish translation] Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 254 p. Cf. Pioneer (1942) and Pathfinder (1973) imprints, 1977.
    - Trotsky, Leon. El programa de transicion [The Transitional Program. Spanish translation] Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 203 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1973) imprint, 1977.
    - Trotsky, Leon. La revolucion de octubre. Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 249 p., 1977.
    - Trotsky, Leon. La revolucion traicionada: Que es y a donde va la Union Sovietica? [The Revolution Betrayed. Spanish translation] Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 298 p. Cf. Pioneer (1945) and Pathfinder (1972) imprints, 1977. (Box 38)
    - Waters, Mary-Alice. Marxismo y feminismo. Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 173 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1972) imprint, 1977.
    - Trotsky, Leon. Obras. Madrid: Akal Editor, Volumes 1, 4-6, 1977-1979.
    - Hansen, Joseph. Introduccion al programa de transicion. By Joseph Hansen and George Novack. Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 95 p., 1978.
    - Trotsky, Leon. Su moral y la nuestra [Their Morals and Ours. Spanish translation] Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 78 p. Cf. Pioneer (1942), Merit (1966) and Pathfinder (1972) imprints, 1978.
    - Novack, George. Introduccion a la logica: Logica formal y logica dialectica [An Introduction to the Logic of Marxism. Spanish translation] Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 154 p., 1979.
    - ----------. Mexican edition. Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 154 p. Cf. Related U.S. (1942), Pioneer (1963), Merit (1966) and Pathfinder (1971) imprints, 1984.
    - Trotsky, Leon. La revolucion permanente [The Permanent Revolution. Spanish translation] Edited by Jose Eugenio Stoute. 2nd edition. Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 258 p. Cf. Pioneer (1931), Merit (1969) and Pathfinder (1986) imprints, 1979.
    - Reed, Evelyn. La evolucion de la mujer: Del clan matriarcal a la familia patriarcal [Woman's Evolution. Spanish translation] Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 350 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1974) imprint, 1980.
    - Novack, George. Democracia y revolucion: De los griegos a nuestros dias [Democracy and Revolution. Spanish translation] 2nd edition. Barcelona: Editorial Fontamara, 298 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1971) imprint, 1982.
    - X, Malcolm. Vida y voz de un hombre negro: Autobiografia y seleccion de discursos. Navarra: Txalaparta, 244 p., 1991.
  - Sri Lanka
    - Cannon, James P. [The Twenty-fifth Anniversary of the Russian Revolution. Sinhalese translation] Colombo: Lanka Samasamaja, 13 p., 1951. (Box 39)
    - Trotsky, Leon. The Class Nature of the Soviet State. Colombo: Lanka Samasamaja, 22 p. Cf. Pioneer (1934) imprint, 1952.
    - Trotsky, Leon. The Only Road. Colombo: Lanka Samasamaja, 88 p. Reprint of Pioneer Publishers edition (1933, q.v.), 1959.
  - Sweden
    - X, Malcolm. Malcolm X talar [Malcolm X Speaks. Swedish translation] Edited by George Breitman. Stockholm: Raben och Sjogren, 239 p. Cf. Merit (1965) and Pathfinder (1989) imprints, 1969.
    - Blanco, Hugo. Jord eller dod! Bondernas kamp i Peru [Land or Death. Swedish translation] Stockholm: Forum, 183 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1972) imprint, 1974.
    - Reed, Evelyn. Kvinnans utveckling: Fran matriarkalisk klan till patriarkalisk familj [Woman's Evolution. Swedish translation] Stockholm: Bokforlaget Roda Rummet, 527 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1974) imprint, 1978.
    - Harsch, Ernest. Sydafrika: Vit makt, svart revolt [South Africa. Swedish translation] Stockholm: Bokforlaget Roda Rummet, 370 p. Cf. Monad (1983) imprint, 1985.
    - Castro, Fidel. Det vi gor idag ar den basta hyllningen till Che [Speech on the Twentieth Anniversary of the Death of Che Guevara. Swedish translation] Stockholm: Catharina Tirsen, 38 p., 1988.
    - Novack, George. "Individens roll i historien." In Fjarde Internationalen. Stockholm: Bokforlaget Roda Rummet, ca. 1990s
  - Turkey
    - Mandel, Ernest. Marksist yabancilasma kurami [The Marxist Theory of Alienation. Turkish translation] By Ernest Mandel and George Novack. Istanbul: Yucel Yayinlari, 127 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1970) imprint, 1975.
    - Reed, Evelyn. Kadinin evrimi: Anaerkil klandan ataerkil aileye [Woman's Evolution. Turkish translation] Istanbul: Payel Yayinevi, 2 volumes. Cf. Pathfinder (1974) imprint, 1982.
  - Venezuela. Mandela, Nelson. Intensifiquemos la lucha: Discursos en Africa, Europa y Norteamerica [Intensify the Struggle against Apartheid. Spanish translation] Caracas: Editorial Nueva Sociedad, 108 p. Cf. Pathfinder (1990) imprint, 1991.
- SOUND RECORDINGS, 1988.
  Recordings of interview used in preparation of a Pathfinder Press book.
  - Three phonotape cassette recordings of interview of Charles Shipman, Mexican-American communist, conducted by Robert Dees, concerning the 2nd World Congress of the Communist International, See also UNPUBLISHED MATERIAL and PHOTOGRAPHS, 1920. (Cassette-cabinet 1-3)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1988.
  Photographs taken at interview used in preparation of a Pathfinder Press book.
  - Eight prints of Charles Shipman, Mexican-American communist, at time of interview conducted by Robert Dees. See also UNPUBLISHED MATERIAL and SOUND RECORDING (Photo-file file)
- INCREMENTAL MATERIALS, PART I (Box 40-49)
  - Pathfinder Press Working Materials, 1993-1995. (Box 40)
    Drafts, notes, translations and printed matter used in preparation of Pathfinder Press publications. See also Audiotapes
    - Congress of the Peoples of the East (1920: Baku, Azerbaijan). To See the Dawn: Baku, 1920: First Congress of the Peoples of the East. Edited by John Riddell. New York: Pathfinder Press, 1993 (Box 40)
      - General. Printed articles (Folder 40: 1)
      - Daghestan material. Drafts, notes and printed articles (Folder 40: 2)
      - Dutch Communist Party appeal. Printed copy and typed translation (Folder 40: 3)
      - Qadir, Fazil al-. Note, printed articles and typed translation (Folder 40: 4)
      - Russian Communist Party material. Photocopies of minutes and declarations re work in the Far East, and printed articles (Folder 40: 5)
      - Sneevliet, Henk. Printed articles and typed translation (Folder 40: 6)
    - Lenin, V. I. Lenin's Final Fight: Speeches and Writings, 1922-23. Edited by George Fyson. New York: Pathfinder Press, 1995 (Folder 40)
      - Georgia. Photocopy of report (Folder 40: 7)
      - National question. Notes on and photocopy of Russian Communist Party 12th Congress discussion proceedings (Folder 40: 8)
      - Trotsky, Leon. Photocopies of letters and writings (Folder 40: 9)
  - Pioneer Publishers English-Language Imprints, 1936-1962. (Box 41)
    All published in New York City unless otherwise noted
    - Trotsky, Leon. The Third International after Lenin. Translated by John G. Wright; with an introduction and explanatory notes by Max Shachtman.357 p., 1936 (Box 41)
    - Leon, A. The Jewish Question: A Marxist Interpretation. Introduction by E. Germain. Mexico City: Ediciones Pioneras, 232 p., 1950 (Box 41)
    - Hansen, Joseph. The Truth about Cuba. 1960.48 p., 1962 (Box 41)
    - Hansen, Joseph. The Theory of the Cuban Revolution. 30 p., 1962 (Box 41)
    - Hansen, Joseph. Trotskyism and the Cuban Revolution: An Answer to Hoy. 15 p., 1962 (Box 41)
  - Pathfinder Press English-Language Imprints, 1993-2002. (Box 41)
    All published in New York City
    - Cannon, James P. Notebook of an Agitator. Third edition.379 p., 1993 (Box 41)
    - Koppel, Martin. Peru's Shining Path: Anatomy of a Reactionary Sect. First printing.35 p., 1993 (Box 41)
    - Mandela, Nelson. Nelson Mandela Speaks: Forging a Democratic Nonracial South Africa. Edited by Steve Clark. Published by Pathfinder Press in association with David Philip and Mayibuye Books.296 p., 1993 (Box 41)
    - The Truth about Yugoslavia: Why Working People Should Oppose Intervention. Edited by George Fyson. First edition.9 p., 1993 (Box 41)
    - Barnes, Jack. The Changing Face of U. S. Politics: Working-Class Politics and the Trade Unions. Edited by Steve Clark. Second expanded edition.459 p., 1994 (Box 41)
    - Castro, Fidel. The Second Declaration of Havana: With the First Declaration of Havana. Second edition.45 p., 1994 (Box 41)
    - Guevara, Ernesto. The Bolivian Diary of Ernesto Che Guevara. Edited by Mary-Alice Waters. First edition.467 p., 1994 (Box 41)
    - Craine, Naomi. Why Is Mark Curtis Still in Prison? 79 p., 1995 (Box 41)
    - Dobbs, Farrell. Teamster Rebellion. Seventh printing.218 p., 1995 (Box 41)
    - Kutcher, James. The Case of the Legless Veteran. Second printing.309 p., 1995 (Box 41)
    - Lenin, V. I. Lenin's Final Fight: Speeches and Writings, 1922-23. Edited by George Fyson. First edition.320 p., 1995 (Box 42)
    - Novack, George. Genocide against the Indians: Its Role in the Rise of U. S. Capitalism. Eighth printing.46 p., 1995 (Box 42)
    - The Politics of Chicano Liberation. Edited by Olga Rodriguez. Second printing.1 86 p., 1995 (Box 42)
    - Trotsky, Leon. In Defense of Marxism: The Social and Political Contradictions of the Soviet Union. Fourth edition. 342 p., 1995 (Box 42)
    - Trotsky, Leon. Marxism and Terrorism. Second edition. 30 p., 1995 (Box 42)
    - Craine, Naomi. A Packinghouse Worker's Fight for Justice: The Mark Curtis Story. 83 p., 1996 (Box 42)